All right, so for the בבלי Bavli today's דף daf is דף
ד, Daf Dalet, we pick up at the bottom of ג עמוד
ב, Gimmel Amud Bet, the first second wide line, and we're dealing
with the sources about how do you know that you need a
בית דין beis din of three,
and now we get to the teaching of רבי, Rebbi, which we've
seen in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our rabbis taught.
דיני ממונות בשלושה, Dinei mamonot bishlosha, you need three. רבי אומר בחמישה,
Rebbi omer bachamisha, five. So here we've got a ברייתא beraisa that
explicitly says that. Apparently it's a תוספתא. Tosefta. In the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
it sort of sounded like they were extrapolating it. כדי שיגמור דין
בשלושה. Kdei sheyigmor din bishlosha. Why do you need five? So three
judges in the end make the final decision for either merit or
for innocence or guilt. אלמא, Alma, says the גמרא, Gemara, בתלתא, bitlasa,
אלמא קסבר תלתא דכתיבי בגמר דין כתיבי. alma kasavar tlasa kiksivi b'gmar
din ksivi. So רבי Rebbi understands that the three, the אלהים... Elohim...
did I skip a line? אטו בתלתא מי לא גמר דינא? Atu
bitlasa mi lo gamar dina? בתרי? Bitrei? What do you mean you
need three to make a final judgment? If you have a בית
דין beis din of three, the judgment will be done by two?
Why should you need three to make a final judgment? No, הכי
קאמר. hachi ka'amar. Here's what it means. מפני שגמר דין בשלושה, Mipnei
shegmar din bishlosha, because not because because we start with the assumption
that the גמר דין gmar din is done by three. It's not
like you whatever meaning okay
move in one direction.
Yeah, you need three finding in which either side is the majority
side, it has to have three on that side. אלמא קסבר תלתא
דכתיבי בגמר דין כתיבי. Alma kasavar tlasa kiksivi b'gmar din ksivi. Ah,
so he understands not that it's impossible to have a בית דין
beis din of three and decide by two but that the פסוק
pasuk requires it. So he understands that the פסוקים psukim require of
אלהים, Elohim, it is a requirement of three in the actual side
that is finding for guilt or innocence. And so, מגדף בה רבי
אבא. m'gadif bah Rebbi Abbo. רבי אבא Rebbi Abbo would like curse
this or you know מקפיד makpid this. And it was the same
רבי אבא Rebbi Abbo in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi by the way, you
can compare it. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, תהא סנהדרין גדולה צריכה מאה
וארבעים ואחד? t'hei sanhedrin gedola tzericha me'ah ve'arbaim ve'echad? So if that's
true, that the side finding in you know the majority side has
to have the right number... three, twenty-three, seventy-one, so does the major
בית דין beis din need a hundred and forty? So that you
can have a שבעים ואחד shivim ve'echad so that you can have
a שבעים ואחד shivim ve'echad finding in one side? כדי שיגמור דין
בשבעים ואחד, Kdei sheyigmor din b'shivim ve'echad, ותהא סנהדרין קטנה דעשרים ותלתא
צריכים ארבעים וחמישה. v'tehei sanhedrin ktana d'esrim v'tlasa tzerichim arbaim v'chamisha. Forty-five.
כדי שיגמור דין בשלושה ועשרים Kdei sheyigmor din bishlosha ve'esrim so you
have twenty-three finding as the majority. אלא, Ela, we don't say that.
Rather what do we say? אספה לי שבעים איש אמר רחמנא, Esfi
li shivim ish amar Rachmana, משעת אסיפה שבעים. mishas asifa shivim. Gather
me seventy people, the convocation is seventy. Seventy isn't the number that
signs for innocence or guilt, they're the number of the entire unit.
ושפטו העדה והצילו העדה, V'shaftu ha'eida v'hitzilu ha'eida, נמי משעת שיתות העדה.
nami mishas shitos ha'eida. So we say that that means the ten
and the ten and the twenty-three, that's the entire group. That's not
one side of the of the finding guilt. הכא נמי, hacha nami,
here too. ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים. V'nikrav ba'al habayis el ha'Elohim.
They come to the judges. משעת קריבה שלושה. Mishas kriva shlosha. The
body is a body of three. Where do you get the idea
that the side finding for innocence or guilt has to be the
full number?
So, אלא היינו טעמא דרבי. ela hainu ta'ama d'Rebbi. Fine, it's not
just that we say, oh, three, three means that that's the side
finding for innocence or guilt. Because then you would say twenty-three is
the side finding for innocence or guilt. So it has to be
a more close read of the פסוק. pasuk. So here's רבי's Rebbi
reasoning. אשר ירשיען אלהים. Asher yarshiun Elohim. The judges find guilty, and
the language ירשיען yarshiun is in plural. So that's two judges are
finding guilty. Now you could stop there. Two judges find guilty, perfect,
a בית דין beis din of three. But תרי. trei. So that
means two. Now, why don't we just stop there? That's a בית
דין beis din of three, two find guilty. No. נאמר אלהים למטה
ונאמר אלהים למעלה. Nemar Elohim lemata v'nemar Elohim lemala. It says אלהים
Elohim here finding guilt, אשר ירשיען, asher yarshiun, and it says אלהים
Elohim at the beginning of the פסוק, pasuk, עד האלהים יבוא דבר
שניהם. ad ha'Elohim yavo devar shneihem. So when it's coming to the
judges, it can't be coming to two because אין בית דין שקול.
ein beis din shakul. It would have to come to three. So
since the אלהים Elohim at the beginning, the body, is a body
of three, אשר ירשיען אלהים asher yarshiun Elohim has to also be
a body of three finding for innocence or guilt. Okay, and the
whole בית דין beis din is five.
מה למטה שנים אף למעלה שנים. Ma lemata shnayim, af lemala shnayim.
The same way we've now said ירשיען yarshiun is two, above when
it says... so two for finding guilt, that works. But now we
say that the אלהים Elohim that you come to, the body, the
בית דין beis din is made of two as well. That's the
אלהים Elohim in the top of the פסוק. pasuk. But we had
to go from the bottom to the top because the top did
not refer to it in the plural. So אלהים Elohim in the
top could have meant one. But since אשר ירשיען אלהים asher yarshiun
Elohim means two, then the אלהים Elohim in the beginning of the
פסוק, pasuk, when there's a body you come to, means two as
well. Now that that means two, but it can't mean two, it
has to mean
three, אין בית דין שקול. ein beis din shakul. מוסיפין עליהם עוד
אחד הרי כאן חמישה. Masifin aleihem od echad, harei kan chamisha. So
here it says ונקרב בעל הבית אל האלהים. V'nikrav ba'al habayis el
ha'Elohim. That could be one judge. But then it says אשר ירשיען
Asher yarshiun in the plural אלהים, Elohim, that's two judges. So if
this, because of this, is two, so this אלהים Elohim is two,
but you're not coming to a בית דין beis din of two,
אין בית דין שקול. ein beis din shakul. so you're coming to
a בית דין beis din of three. Okay, so if you've got
three here, and it's not exactly three, they're saying three plus two
gets you five, or are they saying if this אלהים elohim now
means three, then this אלהים elohim now means three, that's how I
think it's reading it. And therefore if three are finding for guilt,
the whole בית דין beis din must be made out of five.
Okay, and why do we read it that way? It says because
מה למטה שנים אף למעלה שנים. ma lemata shenayim af lemala shenayim.
So the bottom is two, so the top is two, that's four.
אין בית דין שקול, ein beis din shakol, you add one.
You mean you're just sort of saying two and two and then
that's four? Yeah, maybe. You yeah, I guess so. But then the
question is that why why do you have to read these as
separate? Why do you read why do you I guess because we've
been adding up the אלהיםs elohim until now anyway. So but why
do you add? Why don't you just say the same two here
is the two up here? But you're right. Okay, you're probably right.
He's just probably I hear what you're saying. Fine. He's just adding
them. Okay, I guess the way I'm doing it also gets you
to the statement that עד שיגמר הדין בשלושה. ad sheyigamer hadin bishlosha.
It gets you to the idea that the ירשיעון אלהים yarshi'un elohim
is being read as this means three are finding for guilt. Whereas
if you just say this is two and this is two and
that's four plus one is five, it's not underscoring the importance of
יגמר הדין בשלושה. yigamer hadin bishlosha. But either way, that's how he
gets to his idea of five. Okay,
הרי כאן חמישה. harei kan chamisha. ורבנן, verabbanan, and what do the
Rabbis say back? ירשיאן כתיב. yarshi'an kesiv. It doesn't say it does
it's not it's written without the ו. vov. And therefore, since it's
written without the ו, vov, you cannot get this to mean two.
The reason you got this to mean two is the verb here
was in the plural. Okay, but since it's written without the ו
vov you can't דרשן darshan even though it's read as ירשיעון, yarshi'un,
you can't דרשן darshan this as two, you can only דרשן darshan
this as one, so it's one, two, three, it's three judges, it's
not two, four, five, which is five judges.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So now
we shift. Yes. Now, okay, so that's just what we saw again
in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well that רבי Rebbi has this idea
of five. יגמר הדין בשלושה. yigamer hadin bishlosha. And now we're going
to spend the rest of today's דף daf or all of today's
דף daf because now we're at the beginning of the דף, daf,
discussing nothing to do with סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Just this question about whether
you make דרשות drashos based on the way the פסוק pasuk is
read or the way the פסוק pasuk is written. Okay. Exactly. אמר
רבי יצחק, amar Rabbi Yitzchak, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
or whatever, רבי יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
רבי ורבי יהודה בן רועץ, Rebbi veRabbi Yehuda ben Roeitz, whoever heard
of a רבי יהודה בן רועץ, Rabbi Yehuda ben Roeitz, ובית שמאי
ורבי שמעון ורבי עקיבא, uveit Shammai veRabbi Shimon veRabbi Akiva, all these
תנאים, Tannaim, כולו סבירא להו kulu sevira lehu they're all of the
opinion יש אם למקרא. yesh em lemikra. There is the mother to
the way it is read, like the I guess mother sense of
gives birth to the interpretations, okay, that the way we interpret things
hermeneutically is actually is based on the way yeah is
based on the way it is read out loud in the synagogue
and so on. Okay.
יש אם למקרא yesh em lemikra over...?
Well, it's an oral תורה Torah of around the written תורה. Torah.
It's sort of like the whole story about you know about בית
הלל Beis Hillel that says one day he teaches him אלף בית
גימל, alef beis gimmel, the next day he teaches the גר ger
גימל בית אלף, gimmel beis alef, and he says look you trusted
me to you know you have to trust me even when it
comes to stuff in writing. So here too, there's the written text
but how to read the written text has to do with a
tradition you know. The interesting thing is that the word מסורת masores
doesn't mean the tradition for reading, מסורת masores means the way it
is written, and מקרא mikra means the way it is read. So
it's it's a little hard to remember what each word yeah.
מקרא mikra means
read, but why does מסורת masores mean the way it's written? Okay,
you know it's because it's a tradition of a scribal tradition. I
understand. Anyway.
מקרא mikra really has to mean I understand.
Okay. So they all of all of these say that the דרשות
drashos go by the way it is read, not by the way
it is written. So now we're going to go through this. רבי
הדאמרן, Rebbi had'amaran, רבי Rebbi we said. ירשיעון yarshi'un in the plural
means two. Two plus two plus one gets you five. Okay. רבי
יהודה בן רועץ דתניא, Rabbi Yehuda ben Roeitz detanya, great little ברייתא.
braisa. שאלו תלמידיו את רבי יהודה בן רועץ, sha'alu talmidav es Rabbi
Yehuda ben Roeitz, the students asked Yehuda ben Roeitz. I haven't looked
if Yehuda ben Roeitz appears anywhere else in תלמודיק Talmudic literature. Anyway.
אקרא אני שבעים. ekra ani shiv'im. Okay. יכול תהא יולדת נקבה טמאה
שבעים. yachol tehei yoledes nekeiva teme'ah shiv'im. It says when a woman
gives birth to a boy it says you know that she's what
does it say? אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר וטמאה שבעת ימים, isha
ki tazria veyalda zachar vetame'a shivas yamim, seven
days. כימי נדת דותה תטמא. kimei nidas devosah tisma. But it says
ואם נקבה תלד וטמאה שבועים כנדתה. ve'im nekeiva seled vetame'a shevu'ayim kenidasah.
But the שבועים shevu'ayim is not written with a ו. vov. So
if it's it's written without the ו, vov, so you could read
it וטמאה שבעים כנדתה. vetame'a shiv'im kenidasah. Maybe she's טמאה teme'ah for
seventy days. Okay. תהא יולדת נקבה טמאה שבעים. tehei yoledes nekeiva teme'ah
shiv'im. אמר להן amar lahen he said back to them טימא וטיהר
בזכר וטימא וטיהר בנקבה. tima vetiher bezachar vetima vetiher benekeiva. No, let's
look by the analogy. By a male there's a period of טומאה
tumah and then a period of טהרה, tahara, right, that she sits
you know בדמי bidmei
what is it? ושלשים ושלש... ushloshim veshalosh... אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר
וטמאה שבעת ימים כימי נדת דותה תטמא וביום... isha ki tazria veyalda
zachar vetame'a shivas yamim kimei nidas devosah tisma veyom... And thirty days
and thirty, what is
it? ושלשים יום ושלשת ימים תשב על דמי טהרה. v'shloshim yom u'shloshet
yamim tshev al dmei taharah. So for thirty-three days, even if she
bleeds, she's טהור. tahor. And by a girl for sixty-six days, even
if she bleeds, she's good, she's טהור. tahor. So there's this parallel.
טימא וטיהר בזכר וטימא וטיהר בנקבה. Tima v'tihar b'zachar v'tima v'tihar b'nekeivah.
מה שטיהר בזכר Mah she'tihar b'zachar when the period of her being
pure, even if she bleeds, by a male child, מה שטיהר בזכר
בנקבה כפליים. mah she'tihar b'zachar b'nekeivah kiflayim. The female is twice as
long. The male is the thirty-three day period of דם טהור, dam
tahor, and the female is sixty-six. There's no other way to read
the פסוקים psukim than thirty-three and sixty-six. So the female is double.
אף כשטימא בזכר, Af keshetima b'zachar, so when it says the male
is, she's טמאה tmeiah when she gives birth for seven days, בנקבה
כפליים. b'nekeivah kiflayim. So the female is double, it's two weeks. So
clearly the word of the פסוק pasuk is שבועים, shvuayim, two weeks,
and not שבעים. shivim. Okay, that's obviously a very פשט pshat read
of the פסוק. pasuk. Fine. So that's how he knew that it
meant two weeks and not seventy because by analogy of the טהור
tahor days to the טמא tamei days. ולאחר שיצאו, V'achar she'yatzeu, after
the students left, יצא ומחזר אחריהם. Yatza u'machzer achareihem. He was going
and running after them and trying to like, you know, get back,
you know, to retract or to pull, not to pull them back.
Okay. Going after them and finding them. אמר להם, Amar lahem, and
he said to them, אי אתם זקוקים לכך. Iy atem zkukim l'kach.
You know, you don't need the point I made. Of course the
point I made is right. It's clear the פשט pshat in the
פסוקים psukim is two weeks. But you don't even need to say
that. Why do you not need to say that? שבועים קרינן ויש
אם למקרא. Shvuayim karinan v'yesh eim l'mikra. Because it doesn't matter. The,
we read it in, we know that we read it as two
weeks. It doesn't matter that it's read, written in a way that
in theory could be read as seventy. You have to give primacy
to our tradition of how it's read. Right? Now, it seems like
that's really an interesting point because he, you know, the point he
made was an excellent read of the פסוקים psukim in terms of
the, you know, parallel. The הלכה halacha was the same. But he
wanted to make sure that in the future they would like not
start wondering, wait, I could read it this way, I could read
it that way. Right? It's a really important point to know when
it comes to הלכה halacha issues, you have got to give weight
to our traditions of how it's read and not, and not so
just focus on the, you know, the word. By the way, I
think this is such an important, first of all, important to note
that this phrase יש אם למקרא yesh eim l'mikra presumably comes from
this story. Okay? I don't know where else it's, I mean the
גמרא Gemara uses it, but presumably it's derived from this story. But
the other thing is, as I was saying before in the whole
story about, you know, בית הלל Beit Hillel and the גר ger
and so on, it's a really important point of תורה שבעל פה.
Torah she'baal peh. It's like, how do you engage? You sort of
say, well, I got these written words and now I don't, I'm
going to pretend like I don't even know how they're read and
I'm going to סתם stam speculate in different ways to read them.
And he says, no, that's not the way it goes. You know,
the point of departure is not, even with the תורה שבכתב, Torah
she'biktav, the point of departure is not just the written word. Even
when we start doing our rabbinic enterprise of interpreting תורה שבכתב, Torah
she'biktav, the point of departure is how our, how we know those
words were meant to be read. What our traditions are for how
those words are meant to be read. And therefore you should just
forget your, you know, it's read שבועים shvuayim and that's the end
of the discussion. Yes.
That's interesting that he taught it first the logical and then the
formalistic. Right.
Usually you reverse them. Look, this is how we read and anyway
let me back it up for you. But in a way there's
something more powerful for this because if I tell to you, look,
this is how we read it and I'm going to prove it
to you from the פסוקים, psukim, then in the end what you're
left with is any claim that this is how we read it
needs backup proof. Whereas this way, the lesson is much more powerful.
Look, if you want me to, I could prove it to you
that that's the פשט. pshat. But at the end of the day,
it doesn't matter whether I can prove it to you or not.
We go by how, what, how this is read. That's a much
more powerful message of יש אם למקרא. yesh eim l'mikra. Yes.
It also though I think does give a lot of authority to
סברא svara of, in other words, if you don't have a מסורה,
mesorah, right, you don't have a way
of, sure, right.
But the end message here is is that... Right, exactly. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, so that's sort of seems as like
the prime story of this discussion of יש אם למקרא. yesh eim
l'mikra.
But does he, is there another time that he says? He does.
In the same context about יש אם
למקרא.
yesh eim
l'mikra.
Another time in סיפרא Sifra but I couldn't find.
Wow, interesting. Okay. בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Now בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
where's בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? תנן. Tnan. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai
omrim, כל הניתנין על מזבח החיצון שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר. kol hanitnin
al mizbe'ach hachitzon shenatan b'matanah achat kiper. All the bloods that are
put on the outer altar, you know, the main outdoor at the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Even though the תורה Torah says that you're
supposed to put it סביב. saviv. You זורק zorek the blood of
the עולה olah or of the שלמים shlamim סביב. saviv. So the
way חז"ל Chazal understand this סביב saviv is, you know, you could
have sort of said maybe you're supposed to draw a line around
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The way they understand it is that you throw
it on two corners, וזרקו את הדם על המזבח סביב, v'zarku et
hadam al hamizbe'ach saviv, on two opposite corners so they hit all
four walls. Okay, that's the עולה olah and the שלמים. shlamim. Okay,
the עולה, Olah, the שלמים, Shelamim, the אשם, Asham, all of those
things, I don't know, not the אשם, Asham, whatever, all of those
things, check אשם, Asham, all of those things if you know if
it was only one placing of blood and then בדיעבד bedi'eved that's
fine. Okay.
So where are we? Oh, אשם Asham I was right, I'm sorry,
it is אשם, Asham, thank you. Just checking רש״י. Rashi. Okay, אשם.
Asham. Fine. Okay. So it says, בית שמאי אומרים כל הניתנים על
המזבח החיצון שנתן מתנה אחת כיפר. Beit Shammai omrim kol hanitnim al
hamizbeach hachitzon shenatan matana achat kipper. Even one placing of blood works,
שנאמר she'ne'emar we'll read the פסוק pasuk here ודם זבחיך ישפך. v'dam
zvachecha yishapech. The blood of your sacrifice shall be spilled, so one
שפיכה shfichah בדיעבד bedi'eved is enough. ובחטאת שתי מתנות. U'v'chatat shtei matanot.
Now
the חטאת Chatat normally was put not there but was על קרנות
המזבח. al karnot hamizbeach.
Okay? I mean anyway if you sort of think about it, right,
here's the מזבח, Mizbeach, here's the קרנות karnot whatever, there's the קרנות,
karnot, so the blood of the other sacrifices goes there. חטאת Chatat
blood goes on the קרנות karnot and it goes on all four
קרנות. karnot. Okay, that's where the חטאת Chatat blood goes. So it
says, ובחטאת שתי מתנות. u'v'chatat shtei matanot. בדיעבד Bedi'eved you're supposed to
do all four, but if you did two, that works.
ובית הלל אומרים אף בחטאת שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר. U'Veit Hillel omrim
af b'chatat shenatan b'matana achat kipper. Even by a חטאת Chatat if
you only put blood on one of the horns, you are יוצא
yotzei בדיעבד. bedi'eved. So what's that debate about? What the minimum number
of for the חטאת Chatat is? ואמר רב הונא מאי טעמא דבית
שמאי? V'amar Rav Huna mai ta'ama d'Beit Shammai? What's the reasoning of
Beit Shammai? קרנות קרנות קרנות. Karnot, karnot, karnot. הרי כאן שש. Harei
kan shesh. It says you should put the blood when it speaks
about the different חטאות chataot at the end of פרשת ויקרא, parshat
Vayikra, you know, it speaks about multiple חטאות chataot and with each
one it says put it on the קרנות המזבח, karnot hamizbeach, the
corners of the altar. So it says the word קרנות karnot in
those פרשיות, parshiyot, in those, you know, sections, a total of three
times. So three times two, each the word קרנות karnot by itself
means two, right, minimum is two, that's six. הרי כאן שש. Harei
kan shesh. So but there's only four corners. So why would it
say six if there's only four corners? ארבע למצוה ושתים לעכב. Arba
l'mitzvah u'shtayim l'akev. It must mean four is the way to do
it, you should do it, that's the מצוה, mitzvah, but post facto
what's minimally required is two. That's בית שמאי's's Beit Shammai דרשה. drasha.
So he goes by the way the פסוק pasuk is read because
it's read קרנות karnot in the plural.
ובית הלל אומרים קרנות קרנת קרנת. U'Veit Hillel omrim karnot, karnat, karnat.
Two of them appear without a ו. vav. So you go by
the way it's written. So that gets you starting not with six
but with four. הרי כאן ארבע, Harei kan arba, that's four. Now,
ג' למצוה ואחת לעכב, gimel l'mitzvah v'achat l'akev, so we have to
say of those four, three are
the extra three are the
מצוה mitzvah and one is the minimum requirement. It's a slightly different
דרשה drasha because Beit Hillel the four and the two were the
two weren't included in the four with four plus two, right, בית
שמאי, Beit Shammai, excuse me, thank you. That got six. Beit Hillel
it's four within that four, three are the מצוה mitzvah component and
one is the מעכב me'akev for Beit Hillel. Okay? But anyway that
goes by the way it is written, not the way it is
read. So now the גמרא Gemara says ואימא כולו למצוה? v'eima kulo
l'mitzvah? I don't get it, if we do it in parallel to
the way we read בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, let's say all four
are the לכתחילה l'chatchila
and בדיעבד bedi'eved you need nothing. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
כפרה בלא נתינה לא אשכחן. kapara b'lo ntinah lo ashkechan. You don't
get כפרה kapara without doing a certain act with the blood. Obviously
you need some act of the placing of the blood for כפרה.
kapara. So we're going to read the four as saying, you know,
four is three are extra and one is and one is מעכב.
me'akev. And of course why not just say all four are מעכב?
me'akev? You know, it's a little bit unclear how you get the
idea that anything is a מצוה mitzvah there. Right, why not so
that's not clear. We'll keep we'll have another דרשה drasha later. Anyway,
but that's how we've got it, that they're debating whether you go
by the way it's read or it's written. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
now how about רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דתניא
שתים כהלכתן ושלישית אפילו טפח. detanya shtayim k'hilchatan v'shlishit afilu tefach. What
is the minimum number of walls of a סוכה? Sukkah? So the
חכמים chachamim say two normally and one even a טפח tefach like
if your סוכה Sukkah is something like this. Okay? I mean the
question is where does that טפח tefach go? Okay, so it sort
of, you know, it sort of makes it clear what the shape
is, the rectangle is, but this third wall it's enough if it's
a טפח. tefach. That's how we פסקן pasken and רבי שמעון אומר
שלש כהלכתן ורביעית אפילו טפח. Rabbi Shimon omer shalosh k'hilchatan v'revi'it afilu
tefach. No, no, no, he wants three full walls and the final
fourth wall could be a little טפח. tefach. So elsewhere the גמרא
Gemara says you know maybe he holds סוכה Sukkah is דירת קבע,
dirat keva, he needs more complete walls, but here we're going to
make the issue a דרשה drasha issue. Okay?
במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamiflagi? What's the debate? רבנן סברי יש אם למסור
ורבי שמעון סבר יש אם למקרא. Rabbanan savri yesh em l'masor v'Rabbi
Shimon savar yesh em l'mikra. Do you go by how it's written
or how it's read? רבנן סברי יש אם למסור, Rabbanan savri yesh
em l'masor, you go by how it's written, בסוכת בסוכת בסוכות. basukot,
basukot, basukot. It says you shall dwell in סוכות. sukkot. It says
the word סוכות sukkot three times. Two of them without the ו.
vav. So if you read it without the ו vav and it's
a singular, so and one is with the ו, vav, it's a
plural, that's four.
הרי כאן ארבע, Harei kan arba, that's four walls. חד קרא לגופיה,
Chad kra l'gufeh, now one of the פסוקים pesukim you need this
is sort of like the אין דורשין תחילות. ein dorshin techilot. One
of them you need because the פסוק pasuk has to start by
referring to a סוכה. Sukkah. So that doesn't get to count if
it's the topic. That doesn't get to count towards the number. So
פשו להו ג' תלת, pashlu lehu gimel telat, you're left with three.
So three walls, and אתא הלכתא גרעה לשלישית ואוקמה אטפח. ata hilchesa
gara lishlishis ve'ukma atefach. We have a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
miSinai that one of the walls can even be only a טפח.
tefach. So we start with the Torah telling me three, okay, because
it had four but one was needed to tell me the basic
topic. So we have three and then the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe miSinai says one of those walls can be only a טפח,
tefach, and that's two and a טפח. tefach. That's the חכמים. Chachamim.
רבי שמעון סבר, Rabbi Shimon savar, now Rabbi Shimon holds you go
by how it's read. בסכות בסכות בסכות, basukkot basukkot basukkot, the way
it's read is in the plural, so that gets you six. הרי
כאן שש, harei kan shesh, that's six. חד קרא לגופיה, chad kara
legufei, you need one of those words to basically introduce the topic,
that's אין דורשין תחילות. ein dorshin tehillot. But one of those words
is a double, all the words are a double. So you take
off one of the סוכות, sukkot, you're now left with two סוכות,
sukkot, at four. פשו להו ארבע, pashlu lehu arba, you're left with
four. אתא הלכתא גרעה לרביעית ואוקמה אטפח, ata hilchesa gara l'revi'is ve'ukma
atefach, and the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai says one of
those walls could be even a טפח. tefach. So that gets you
to three and a טפח. tefach. So that's that debate of יש
אם למקרא יש אם למסורת. yesh em lamikra yesh em lamosoret. That's
Rabbi Shimon. By the way, everything here other than the first word
with Rabbi Yehuda ben Roeitz who used the words יש אם למסורת
yesh em lamosoret and when it was exactly about the hermeneutic question,
all of this is pure speculation, right? We're starting from a debate
and it's the גמרא Gemara reading into this debate the question of
how you know, יש אם למקרא יש אם למסורת. yesh em lamikra
yesh em lamosoret. And as we'll see as we continue, maybe there's
other reasons for the debate. Like I just said about the סוכה.
sukkah. Maybe the debate is whether you consider סוכה sukkah to be
a permanent dwelling or temporary dwelling. So there could be other reasons
for the debate. But the גמרא Gemara is interpreting it to be
this question of מקרא mikra versus מסורת. mosoret. Okay, same thing סוכות
sukkot
when you're talking about אלוקים Elokim is the first...
yes, that's what I meant when I said דורשין תחילות, dorshin tehillot,
that was what we said yesterday. Yeah.
You translated הלכתא גרעתא hilchesa gara'ata as הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
miSinai.
Yes.
Well, you mean הלכתא? hilchesa? So in general הלכתא hilchesa is there's
a whole discussion whether הלכתא hilchesa means הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
miSinai or הלכתא hilchesa means a... the הנצי"ב haNetziv discusses this, an
ancient tradition that we don't really have, we don't really know the
reason for. But in סוכה, sukkah, I have to double check, I'm
99% positive that in מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah it explicitly identifies שלישית
אפילו טפח shlishis afilu tefach as a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
miSinai. Okay, but but elsewhere הלכתא hilchesa has a possible different meaning.
There's a debate whether הלכתא hilchesa in general means הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha l'Moshe miSinai or not. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, yeah. The גמרא Gemara is explicit, right? רש"י Rashi mentions, the
גמרא Gemara is explicit that it's הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe miSinai.
Okay, I mean about the wall of a
סוכה. sukkah. Okay. רבי עקיבא דתניא. Rabbi Akiva detanya. Now where is
this Rabbi Akiva? רבי עקיבא אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: מניין לרביעית דם
שבאה משני מתים שמטמאה באהל? minayin l'revi'is dam sheba'ah mishnei meisim shemetame'ah
b'ohel? Now how do you know that, the הלכה halacha is that
the blood that is the size that the rabbis understood was enough
for an infant to survive, you know, for the blood that an
infant could live on when he was just born, which is a
רביעית. revi'is. A רביעית revi'is is a very small amount, it's the
size of your קידוש Kiddush cup, it's three and a half ounces.
Okay, but that amount of blood represents the entire person and therefore
it causes טומאה tumah under a tent, under a ceiling. Okay, there's
טומאה tumah of a dead body which is like a tiny piece
of bone which is not טמא tamei if it's under a roof,
but any טומאה tumah that represents the whole body, a כזית kezayit
of the flesh, a certain number of bones, a certain amount of
of of blood, is causes טומאה באהל. tumah b'ohel. So Rabbi Akiva
says how do I know if that minimum amount of blood came
from two different dead bodies? If the idea is for it to
represent a body, maybe it all has to come from the same
body. Okay, so from the same corpse. So מניין לרביעית דם שבאה
משני מתים? minayin l'revi'is dam sheba'ah mishnei meisim? How do I know
when it comes from two corpses and you have the minimum amount?
שמטמאה באהל shemetame'ah b'ohel it causes טומאה tumah under a roof? שנאמר
shene'emar the verse says: על כל נפשת מת לא יבא. al kol
nafshot meit lo yavo. You should not enter into, which means enter
under the same roof, of all dead souls. And here and the
דרשה drasha is that the נפשות nafshot refers to blood, כי הדם
הוא הנפש, ki hadam hu hanefesh, like blood and נפש nefesh go
together. So he says: שתי נפשות shtei nafshot נפשות nafshot is plural,
two different souls, two different corpses, ושיעור אחד v'shiur echad but it's
one size. How do you know it's one size? Because it says
נפשת מת. nafshot meit. It doesn't say נפשת מתים. nafshot meisim. Okay,
so therefore even the minimum amount which is which represents a dead
body מת, meit, one minimum amount from two נפשות. nafshot. Okay, that
causes טומאה באהל. tumah b'ohel. ורבנן v'rabbanan and the rabbis say back:
נפשת כתיב. nafshat ketiv. No, no, no, it's written without the ו,
vav, so you can't make that דרשה. drasha. Again, that's the גמרא
Gemara reading that into the rabbinic response. Okay, and therefore it all
has to be from one dead body. So here's how we have
them all saying יש אם למקרא. yesh em lamikra. So now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say, going to challenge this. מתקיף לה
רב אחא. matkif lah Rav Acha. מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב
*Maskif la Rav Aha bar Yaakov*. רב אחא בר יעקב *Rav Aha
bar Yaakov* challenged this. מי דאית ליה יש אם למקרא yesh em
lemikra. *Mi d'is lei Yesh Eim Lamikra*? What do you mean these
תנאים *Tannaim* hold יש אם למקרא yesh em lemikra. *Yesh Eim Lamikra*
and their בר פלוגתא *Bar Pluktas*, you know, the people that the
תנאים *Tannaim* get to disagree with them, reject that? Who could not
hold יש אם למקרא yesh em lamikra. *Yesh Eim Lamikra*? Of course
you have to go by the way we read it. דתניא *De-tanya*,
the ברייתא *Baraita* says: בחלב אמו be-chelev imo, *B'chalav Imo*. Don't cook
a kid in its mother's milk. יכול בחלב *Yachol b'chelev*?
Maybe it doesn't mean its mother's milk, maybe it means don't cook
it in its mother's חלב chalav *Chelev* fat. How do you know
the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* means milk, maybe it means fat? אמרת יש
אם למקרא yesh em lamikra, *Amarta Yesh Eim Lamikra*. So the ברייתא
*Baraita* here, here's again the use of יש אם למקרא yesh em
lamikra *Yesh Eim Lamikra* in this ברייתא *Baraita*. The answer of the
ברייתא *Baraita* is, you know what? I'm not going to try to
prove it to you. That's just the way we read the פסוק
pasuk? *Pasuk*. The way the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* is read is בחלב
*B'chalev*, which means בחלב *B'chalav*, the milk, and not the חלב chelev
*Chelev*. Okay? So look, everybody holds that the איסור *Issur* is meat
in milk. Nobody holds that the איסור *Issur* in the תורה Torah
*Torah* is cooking meat in fat. So of course we have to
go by the way that it's our tradition to read it. So
אלא ela *Ella*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* initially accepts this. Fine.
דכולי עלמא יש אם למקרא yesh em lamikra *D'chulei Alma Yesh Eim
Lamikra*. Everybody agrees you go by the way it's read and that
takes primacy over the way that it's written. Okay, so now how
you gonna explain all the other debates? Okay, so now we're gonna
have to go through every single other debate and say that everybody
agrees you go by the way it's read and we're still gonna
debate it. רבי ורבנן *Rabbi and Rabbanan*, how about the debate of
רבי ורבנן *Rabbi and Rabbanan*, a בית דין din, *Beis Din* of
five versus a בית דין din *Beis Din* of three? בהא קמיפלגי
*B'ha Kamifligi*. רבי סבר savar ירשיעון yarshi'un. אלוהים אחריני *Rabbi savar Yarshiun
Elohim acharini*. So here Jerry Davis, going to what you're saying, so
which is sort of the question I was asking. Everybody agrees that
ירשיעון yarshi'un, אלוהים *Yarshiun Elohim* because of ירשיעון *Yarshiun* means two. The
question is, is it this two and this two? Are is it
a different אלוהים *Elohim* than the אלוהים *Elohim* above? And that's 2
plus 2 is 4 and then it's 5. That's what רבי *Rabbi*
says. Or do you say no, this two is the same two,
and it's all the same two? And therefore you can't have two,
so you get three. Okay? רבי סבר ירשיעון אלוהים אחריני *Rabbi savar
Yarshiun Elohim acharini*, it's a different אלוהים *Elohim*. רבנן Rabbanan סבר ירשיעון
דהאי והאי *Rabbanan savar Yarshiun de-hai v'hai*, it's all the same אלוהים
*Elohim*, this one and that one, it's all the same, it's all
referring to the same בית דין din *Beis Din* of two plus
one gets you three. Okay, but we all agree to read ירשיעון
*Yarshiun* in the plural, that's that. רבי יהודה בן רועית *Rabbi Yehuda
ben Roite*, לא פליגי *Lo pligi*. לא פליגי רבנן Rabbanan עליה *Lo
pligi Rabbanan alei*. רבי יהודה בן רועית *Rabbi Yehuda ben Roite* about
שבעים shiv'im *Shevi'im* and שבועים *Shvu'im*, no, there's no debate there. He
just said, hey, you know how the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*, you know
I know the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* means שבועים *Shvu'im*? Because יש אם
למקרא yesh em lamikra *Yesh Eim Lamikra*. Fine, nobody's going to debate
that. That's, there's not a, there's not an halakhic debate there at
all. בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, now how about this question about the
one versus the four? בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, דתניא *De-tanya*, we learned
a ברייתא *Baraita*: וכיפר וכיפר וכיפר v'chiper v'chiper v'chiper, *V'chiper v'chiper v'chiper*.
So what it says also in all these פסוקים psukim, *Psukim* here
in the פרשת ויקרא *Parshat Vayikra* is you put the blood on
the altar by the חטאת chatas *Chatas* and it will atone for
the person. So the, the underscoring of the idea that it will
atone is understood here to mean even if you do a minimum
amount it will atone. Even if you don't do it exactly the
way we are
prescribing, you know, it'll atone. So it's coming to lower the requirements
at least post-fact. Okay? And if it has three וכיפר v'chiper *V'chiper*s,
you go from putting blood on all four corners, but three, every
וכיפר v'chiper *V'chiper* lowers one. So now okay, it'll be מכפר *Mechaper*
even if you don't do four, even if you only do three.
It'll be מכפר *Mechaper* even if you don't do three, even if
you only do two. Even if you don't do two, even if
you only do one. So we're going to use the וכיפר v'chiper,
*V'chiper*s to get from four to one. Okay, that clear? וכיפר v'chiper
*V'chiper* sort of say it doesn't have to be that much. Okay?
מפני הדין mipnei hadin, *Mipnei Hadin*. Now we needed to דרשן *Darshan*
וכיפר v'chiper *V'chiper* to go down because a logical derivation would have
demanded that all four are required. So now this is a classic
מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halakha*. מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halakha* sort of says logically
we would have required X, so we needed the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*
to tell me Y. And then it says: wait, והלא דין הוא
*V'halo Din Hu*, but logically I could have figured out Y. This
is actually, I should point this out, right, this is a classic
format of מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halakha*. It sort of says, you know,
פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* teaches
X but you know because logically
I would have
said Y. And then it says wait, והלא דין הוא *V'halo Din
Hu*? But logically that,
logically you can say X. And then it goes through a whole
discussion and then it says: no, so you see logically you can't
say X, logically you would have said Y and that's why you
needed the פסוק *Pasuk* to teach you X. Okay, that's like the
funny format. There's actually some nice books that have recently been written
by a guy, I'm trying to remember his name, that sort of
explain, you know, why the whole methodology of תורה שבכתב *Torah Sheb'chsav*
and תורה שבעל פה *Torah Sheba'al Peh*, at least from this school,
this is a particular school of מדרש הלכה *Midrash Halakha*, I forget
if it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Ishmael* or רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, but almost like requires, like you see it's like
in conversation with like, you know, what... I myself would have said
and what the פסוק needs to be teaching me. So I got
it from the פסוק. Why do I, because otherwise I would have
said this. Wait, wait, wait, I could have, you know, who really
even needs a פסוק? I can come to this conclusion myself. No,
no, no, that wouldn't have been your conclusion. So in the end
of the day you did need the פסוק. All right, so that's
what it says. וכיפר v'chiper teaches you, so here וכיפר v'chiper teaches
you, okay, I really need other colors here. All my colors have
gone out on me. וכיפר, v'chiper, anyway, whatever, וכיפר v'chiper teaches you,
וכיפר v'chiper teaches you three, teaches you even one, okay. And then
it says, because of the דין, because the דין would have said
וכיפר v'chiper teaches you even one, that's point number one. Point number
two is, you know, מפני הדין, mipnei hadin, because the דין would
have said four. And now it says, wait, logically maybe I would
have said four, logically maybe I would have said one, and I
don't need the וכיפר to do that. So that's what we're going
to do here, okay? So ולא דין
הוא,
velo din
hu, one minute. Even
without the וכיפר, I logically would have said one and not four.
Why? נאמר דמים למטה ונאמר דמים למעלה. nemar damim lemata venemar damim
lemala. It says דמים damim below and it says דמים damim above.
רש"י Rashi has different explanations what below and above means. We're going
to read the below means when it deals with like, you know,
an אשם asham and a שלמים. shlamim. When it deals with the
other
קרבנות. korbanot. It says blood and when it deals with a חטאת
chatas it says blood. So,
מה דמים האמורים למטה שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר, ma damim ha-amurim lemata
shenatan be-matana achas kiper, the same way by other קרבנות, korbanot, we
know from the earlier דרשה, drasha, ודם זבחיך, vedam zvachecha, we know
that even one placing of blood is enough, אף דמים האמורים למעלה
שניתן במתנה אחת כיפר. af damim ha-amurim lemala shenatan be-matana achas kiper.
So I would have said a חטאת chatas, also, by analogy, also
בדיעבד bedieved one placing of blood. So I could have figured it
out myself. או קל וחומר כדרך זו, o kal vachomer k'derech zu,
or maybe go this way. נאמר דמים בחוץ ונאמר דמים בפנים. nemar
damim bachutz venemar damim bifnim. It says blood by an inner חטאת,
chatas you know, on the inner altar like we bring on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, and it says one on the outer altar. מה
דמים האמורים בפנים, ma damim ha-amurim bifnim, the same way the one
on the inner altar, חיסר אחת מהיתם לא עשה ולא כלום, chiser
achas me-itam lo asa velo klum, even one thing wrong, even doing
one placing of the blood not doing it makes it invalid and
we learn that from פסוקים, pesukim, so אף דמים האמורים בחוץ חיסר
אחת מהיתם לא עשה ולא כלום. af damim ha-amurim bachutz chiser achas
me-itam lo asa velo klum. So maybe the חטאת chatas on the
outer altar should be the same, even missing one placing of blood
is no good. מי דומה למי דומה, mi domeh lemi domeh, which
one should we compare it more to? דמים חוץ מחוץ ואין דמים
חוץ מפנים. damim chutz michutz vein דמים chutz mipnim. Let's compare it
to an outer sacrifice, a חטאת chatas to an עולה, olah, both
on the outer altar, and not to an inner sacrifice. או קל
וחומר כדרך זו, o kal vachomer k'derech zu, or go the opposite,
this way. דמים חטאת וארבע קרנות מחטאת וארבע קרנות. damim chatas ve-arba
kronot michatas ve-arba kronot. Learn a חטאת chatas and four קרנות kronot
that's on the inner altar and compare it to a חטאת chatas
and four קרנות kronot on the outer altar, one's in and one's
out, but they're both a חטאת chatas and they're both four קרנות.
kronot. ואל יוכיח זה שאין חטאת וארבע קרנות. ve-al yochiach zeh she-ein
chatas ve-arba kronot. And don't prove this from the case of an
עולה olah and a שלמים shlamim that is not a חטאת chatas
and is not four קרנות. kronot. Actually that seems like a more
persuasive argument, right? If it's basically the same חטאת chatas and the
same idea of four קרנות, kronot, that should be more of the
comparison. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so that's why, so here's what we
did. We said logically I'm going to say only one. Why would
logically I be able to figure out only one? Based on the
comparison to an עולה olah and a שלמים. shlamim. And the answer
is no, I couldn't have said that because I would have compared
it more to an inner חטאת and would have said you need
all four. So since I can't logically prove one because logically I
would have said four, I need the וכיפר to teach me one.
Okay. So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, וכיפר וכיפר וכיפר,
מפני הדין, I need וכיפר to teach me one because logically I've
just demonstrated that you could have come to the conclusion of four.
Okay.
כיפר אף על פי שלא
נתן אלא שלוש,
kipper af al pi
she-lo natan
ela shalosh, כיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא שתים, kipper af
al pi she-lo natan ela shtayim, כיפר אף על פי שלא נתן
אלא אחת. kipper af al pi she-lo natan ela achas. Every כיפר
kipper saying, you know, we're going, you know, even if you do
a little less, you gain atonement. Okay, we're ready to give you
כפרה. kapara. So we say four but even וכיפר says you know
what? You'll get כפרה kapara even without doing that way, even just
doing three, even just doing two, even just doing one. Okay. All
right. I don't know. Okay. So therefore that's where בית הלל בית
שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai gets it. It has nothing to do
with, you know, with קרנות קרנות קרנות. kronot kronot kronot. It's a
separate דרשה drasha that leads them to come to this conclusion of
one and בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't hold of that דרשה. drasha.
Okay. So that's בית הלל בית שמאי, Beis Hillel Beis Shammai, it's
not about יש אם למקרא. yesh em lamikra. רבי שמעון רבנן, Reb
Shimon Rabbanan, now how about רבי שמעון Reb Shimon and רבנן Rabbanan
about how many walls of a סוכה? sukkah? בהא פליגי, beha pligi,
this is the debate. רבי שמעון Reb Shimon סבר סככה skacha לא
בעי קרא. lo ba'i kra. They all start with סוכות. sukkos. Okay.
And one of the and one word you need for because we're
going like יש אם למקרא. yesh em lamikra. One of the words
you need to tell me the basic topic. So now we're left
with four. But now רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says four, my, you
know. And four becomes three and a bit and you don't need
to use one of those number one of those countings you know
to tell me the idea that a סוכה Sukkah needs סכך. sechach.
Four means four walls minus a bit, three and a
bit.
Yes. Wait, let me just finish this. רבנן סברי סכך בעי קרא.
Rabbanan savri sechach ba'i kra. No, no, no, we start with four,
right? We start with six, and one was for the base, now
we got four. Of those four, we don't just say all four
means four starts with four walls. One of those סכך sechach units
means you need סכך. sechach. Okay? רב שמעון Reb Shimon says no
it's obvious, what is a סוכה Sukkah without סכך? sechach? But the
רבנן Rabbanan... say one of those words, one of those units means
סכך. sechach. So then you're left with three, and for three walls
minus a bit is two and a bit. Okay? So they both
start with six, but רב שמעון Reb Shimon gets down from six
to four and that's four three and a bit, and the רבנן
get from six to three and that's two and a bit. Yes,
רב דב. Reb Dov.
I just want to make sure, so what the גמרא Gemara is
doing right now is there are מחלוקות machlokot in all these עניינים,
inyanim, but they can't be about יש אם למקרא. yesh em lamikra,
Right, everybody holds יש אם למקרא, so trying to clarify how
the what the debate is based on. Correct. As they said, the
יש אם למקרא was really only said by רב יהודה בן ורדיתס
Reb Yehuda ben Rodeites whoever it was and nobody was disagreeing with
him, and the גמרא Gemara read that debate into these debates. And
now the גמרא Gemara is saying everybody holds יש אם למקרא and
we're going to explain these debates based on other considerations.
Do you know that word?
I don't know, it's whatever, to like
shatter? Anyway, רבנן... רבי עקיבא ורבנן בהא פליגי. Rabbi Akiva ve-Rabbanan be-ha
paligi. How about this question about the blood of a dead body?
רבי עקיבא סבר נפשות תרתי משמע, Rabbi Akiva savar nefashot tarti mashma,
two different bodies. רבנן סברי נפשות דעלמא, Rabbanan savri nefashot de-alma, no,
souls. Souls, you know, it means dead bodies as a generic, not
actually two concrete dead bodies. Okay, so now we said everybody could
hold יש אם למקרא because of the פסוק of בחלב אמו, be-chelev
imo. obviously you got to read it, you got to know how
to read it, and these debates are based on something else. But
the גמרא Gemara still not happy. וכולי עלמא יש אם למקרא? ve-chulei
alma yesh em lamikra? Really? Now it's pushing back in the opposite
direction. Everybody agrees it goes by
how it's read? והתניא לטטפת לטטפת לטטפת הרי כאן ארבע. ve-ha tanya
letotafet letotafet letotafet harei kan arba. How do you know your תפילין
של ראש tefillin shel rosh has four compartments? So one דרשה drasha
is לטטפת. totafot. Now לטטפת totafot is plural, okay, that's true, but
twice when the word is written, it's written without the וו. vav.
So that's once. So one, one, two is four. Now that's יש
אם
למסורת, yesh em lamesoret, and it's explicit. He's making that דרשה. drasha.
דברי רבי ישמעאל, divrei Rabbi Yishmael, that's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael,
says. רבי עקיבא אומר אינו צריך, Rabbi Akiva omer eino tzarich, you
don't even have to say that. טט בכתפי שתים פת באפריקי שתים.
tat be-Katfi shtayim pat be-Afriki shtayim. The word לטטפת, totafot, each one
of those words in different languages means two, 2+2 is 4. So
there everybody, both רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל, the two
different basic heads of the hermeneutics, רבי עקיבא doesn't seem to be
disagreeing in principle, he just says it's superfluous. Okay, but they all
seem to be saying יש אם למסורת, yesh em lamesoret, excuse me.
So what's going on? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא fine, we'll
go back to what we said before. לעולם פליגי, le-olam paligi, there
is a major debate of יש אם למקרא יש אם למסורת. yesh
em lamikra yesh em lamesoret.
So now, but now we've got to deal with והני מילי כי
פליגי, ve-hani mili ki paligi, now we've got to deal with the
פסוק of בחלב אמו. If they do disagree, how do we know
that that means milk and not fat for those that say that
you go by the way that it's written? So the גמרא Gemara,
says והני מילי כי פליגי היכא דשני קרא ממסורת. ve-hani mili ki
paligi heicha de-shani kra mi-mesoret. When is there a debate? When the
פסוק is read different than the way it's written. It's written
לטטפת, letotafet, לטטפת, letotafet, and you read it לטטפת. letotafot. It's written
ירשיען yarshi'an and you read it ירשיעון. It's written שבעים and you
read it שבועיים. shevu'ayim. So there you have to make a choice.
Which do you give primacy to? The way that it's read or
the way that it's written when it's written in a way that's
different from the way that it's read? It could have been written
in a better way to reflect the way that it's being read.
That's where there's going to be a debate. אבל האי חלב וחלב
דכי הדדי נינהו. aval hai chelev ve-chalav de-chi hadadi ninhu. There's no
different way to write the word, right? The word חלב chalav? and
חלב chelev are spelled the exact same way. So therefore when there
was, when it's not like the תורה made a point of spelling
it in a different way than it's being read. No, there's nothing
else to do except write those three letters. And therefore we have
to go by the tradition of how those letters are supposed to
be read. In that case, יש אם למקרא. What?
Was there a tradition of חלב? chelev. I mean like I don't
get,
apparently that's what it's saying, that we have traditions of all, יש
אם למקרא. Everybody is agreeing that we have traditions of how to
read these פסוקים, right? That's not being debated. The debate is just,
does the tradition of how it's read trump the way in which
it's written for hermeneutic purposes? So what it's saying here is that
we could discuss when there actually is a divergence between the way
it's read and it's written. Which one do we give primacy to?
But when there's no divergence, of course we're going to, if the
word is read two ways and there was no other way to
spell it, we're going to read it the way that is the
tradition to read it. Okay.
What was the divergence on לטטפת? totafot? How was it...
It could have been written טוטפות totafot with a ו, vav, and
it was written טטפת. totefet. It was written without the ו. vav.
Same thing is true of קרנות. karnot.
Right. So we're going back to everything we said before. All of
the stuff we said before was when there was a division, a
difference between how it's read and it's written, and there there is
a debate: יש אם למקרא, יש אם למסורת. yesh em lamikra yesh
em lamasoret If you ירשיעון, קרנות, karnot, טוטפות, totafot, all those things,
סוכות, sukkot, all those things could have been written with a ו
vav and weren't. And that's why they're being debated, because, because it's
written in a way that's different from how it's read, and that's
why you have two camps on which you should give primacy to
in the דרשה. drasha. But here חלב chalav, is only one way
to read.
Right. Only one way to write. It's only one way to write
חלב. chelev, Exactly.
So now the גמרא, Gemara, last point of the גמרא, Gemara okay,
and that seems like a great answer, right? So and you'd like
to just stop there. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, last question: והרי יראה יראה דכי הדדי נינהו, ve-harei
yera'eh yira'eh de-chi hadadi ninhu, see and be seen like by the
case of appearing, you know, three times in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, whether it means to see or to be seen is written
in the same way, same spelling. ופליגי u-pligi and there's a debate
which one to give to
give primacy to. דתניא יוחנן בן דהבאי אומר משום רבי יהודה בן
תימא הסומא באחת מעיניו פטור מן הראייה. di-tanya Yochanan ben Dahavai omer
mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben Teima ha-suma be-achat me-einav patur min ha-reiyah. Somebody
who is blind in one eye is exempt from appearing in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash on the, you know,
during the רגל, regel, קרבן ראייה, korban reiyah, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, why? It
says יראה יראה. yera'eh yira'eh. So we read it as shall appear
before God. But it's written also as shall see God. So we
are going to say we have we embrace both readings. כדרך שבא
לראות כך בא ליראות. ki-derech she-ba lir'ot kach ba le-hera'ot. The same
way the person comes to see God, the person is come to
be seen by God. And so you're not obligated to be seen
by God unless you're able to see. You don't actually see God,
but unless you're able to see in both of your eyes. מה
לראות בשתי עיניו, mah lir'ot bishtei einav, the same way seeing means
that you were able to see both your eyes, אף ליראות בשתי
עיניו, af le-hera'ot bishtei einav, in order the obligation to appear requires
only if you have, you know, full sight. And therefore but the
rabbis reject that. The rabbis say we don't make the דרשה. drasha.
It's יראה yera'eh and we don't read the יראה yira'eh read, we
don't we only look at read that word the way we have
a tradition to read it. And we don't go by the fact
that it could be read other ways. So there there was no
other way and there's a debate whether you actually give weight to
an alternate reading which is not the traditional way of reading but
based on the way it's written. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר קרא, ela amar Rav Acha
brei de-Rav Ika amar kra, you're right. You know what? Maybe those
that are in the יש אם למסורת yesh em lamasoret. camp will
give weight to alternate readings even if there was no way it
could have been even if there was no divergence of spelling. They
always want to be interested in what the what the word could
be read as and not just how it's read, even if it's
spelled totally naturally. So then why not say that the word by
milk and meat means fat rather than milk? So he says no.
אמר קרא לא תבשל
גדי. amar kra lo tevashel gedi. It talks about cooking. דרך בישול
אסרה תורה. derech bishul asrah Torah. You cook with a liquid. You
don't cook in fat. You know, I mean some people cook in
lard, but that's because it liquefies. Okay? You fry in fat, anyway.
So since it says לא תבשל, lo tevashel, that makes it clear
that the word means חלב, liquid, and not חלב, and not you
know, and not fat. But basically the גמרא was at a great
point which says everybody agrees you go by the way it's written
if it's spelled normally. But if there's a divergence, we're going to
debate. But based on this issue of יראה yera'eh and יראה, yira'eh,
it says you know what, maybe there also is a debate even
if it's spelled normally. But at least in this פסוק of בשר
בחלב, basar be-chalav, there's no question that it means milk because the
context of cooking it's got to mean a liquid and it's not
going to mean a solid. Okay? So that is the end of
that little contained unit about יש אם למקרא יש אם למסורת yesh
em lamasoret and tomorrow we get back to issues of סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.